Randall Araya Campos

Alajuela, Costa Rica

digital.rayado-0e@icloud.com · https://www.linkedin.com/in/randall-araya-campos-689127149/

Bilingual IT professional experienced in IT Infrastructure, Network Administration, and Information Technology Research -both in business and academic settings-. Experience managing different Operating Systems such as GNU/Linux, CentOS, and Windows as well as the administration of OpenLDAP, VPNs (OpenVPN), OpenSSH, and MySQL Server Clustering. Knowledgeable in Cloud tools such as OwnCloud, OpenStack, and all the Amazon Web Services (AWS) catalog. Other experience includes container orchestration, database administration, Big Data, and data mining. Strong skills in embedded systems with Advanced RISC Machine (ARM) technologies. Well established in partnering with stakeholders, business, and project partners. Results-driven and highly trained in fulfilling different tasks within a restricted time frame. Graduated with a Bachelor's degree in Computer Engineering from TEC, Instituto Tecnológico de Costa Rica, ITCR

Work Experience

Snap Technology

Sr. SysOps Engineer

May 2023 – Present

Responsible for infrastructure provisioning, applications build-up, security patches, capacity management, incident, and problem management. Key contributions include:

- Infrastructure as a service ci/cd implementation by bitbucket self hosted runners
- Maintain infrastructure software and operating systems
- Design and implement productive and quality assurance environments. Manually and automatically scripts
- Develop and orchestrate microservices in containers with **Docker and Kubernetes**
- Develop docker files and compose for microservices, with persistent data
- Investigate alternatives to implement services with high-availability performance
- Install orchestrator of **Kubernetes** cluster and resources in with Amazon EC2 virtual machines, physical servers, and spots of Spotinst

Intel

Software Engineer

January 2021 - May 2023

Responsible for application development(full-stack), CI/CD integration, security enhancement, incident and problem solving, key contributions:

- Worked in a DevOps culture, collaborating with development and operations teams to ensure continuous delivery and automated deployment of software. Implemented agile practices and DevOps tools to improve software development efficiency, including automated testing and CI/CD
- Administer and maintain systems support CI/CD on Gitlab and Github with runners hosted on kubernetes
- Vscode plugin development with customizable programming language support
- Code processing with Antlr for handling errors, exceptions and compilation of programming languages
- Implementation of monitoring user experience with New Relic
- Cloud Foundry Application Hosting and Rancher 2
- Jenkins Jobs implementation for automation
- Design, implement and manage solution for script evaluation processes
- Application, server and platform monitoring with New Relic
- Infrastructure design for web pages

Logisticraj

August 2019 - Present

Information Technology Specialist

Responsible for infrastructure provisioning, email service, web developer security patches, capacity management, incident, and problem management. Key contributions include:

- Design, implement and manage solution for web page development
- Administer and maintain systems support CI/CD on Gitlab and Github with runners hosted on Docker and local servers
- Develop and orchestrate microservices in containers for automation

- Provide timely technical support for users and work with them to solve existing problems
- Provide and support email service
- Designand network connectivity

Intel

DevOps Engineer

August 2019 – December 2020

Responsible for infrastructure provisioning, applications build-up, security patches, capacity management, incident, and problem management. Key contributions include:

- Administer and maintain systems support for software, hardware, and servers: test, troubleshoot, diagnose, and resolve all problems
- Provide timely technical support for users and work with them to solve existing problems
- Configure, monitor, and maintain updated virus protection software, and backup data for emergency recovery
- Administration of Windows Servers environments
- Implement smooth migrations between product revisions and application deployments
- Work with agile methodologies such as scrum SAFE
- Works closely with the production release and operations teams to produce consistent, high quality, and solutions to our internal and external customers
- Automate repetitive processes using scripts and API integrations
- Resolve issues of differents teams by automation practices
- Collaborate as an advisor on innovation projects and curses
- Support Microsoft services such as SSIS, SSRS, and SQL server
- Design and implement productive and quality assurance environments. Manually and automatically scripts
- Database migration from MSSQL 2012 to MSSQL 2019
- Responsible for taking requirements for new solutions

Instituto Tecnológico de Costa Rica

July 2019 - December 2019

University professor

Responsible for developing and teaching the introductory programming course. Key contributions include:

- Develop classes, topics, practice, and course schedule
- Evaluate students and present notes
- Implement teaching methodologies for students with different types of learning

Snap Technology IT Systems Administrator

June 2018 - August 2019

Responsible for infrastructure provisioning, applications build-up, security patches, capacity management, incident, and problem management. Key contributions include:

- Administer and maintain systems support for software, hardware, and servers: test, troubleshoot, diagnose, and resolve all problems
- Provide timely technical support for users and work with them to solve existing problems
- Configure, monitor, and maintain updated virus protection software, and backup data for emergency recovery
- Troubleshooting, backup, recovery, and upgrading of company platforms and supporting technical issues
- Administration of Windows Servers, Red Hat, and CentOS Linux environments
- Work with configuration environments; build servers, virtual labs, and tools to accommodate multiple languages and architectures
- Work closely with the production release and operations teams to produce consistent, high quality, and packaged builds for deployment to our internal and external customers
- Deploy and support applications into a highly available environment
- Implement smooth transitions between product revisions and application deployments
- Perform new hardware and Linux OS installations, patching and upgrades

- Maintain infrastructure software and operating systems
- Design and implement productive and quality assurance environments. Manually and automatically scripts
- Develop orchestrate microservices in containers with Docker and Kubernetes
- Develop docker files and compose for microservices, with persistent data
- Investigate alternatives to implement services with high-availability performance
- Install orchestrator of Kubernetes cluster and resources in with Amazon EC2 virtual machines, physical servers, and spots of Spotinst
- Document processes and architecture
- Work in a team with AWS architects to implement solutions with the AWS service catalog
- Work with agile methodologies such as scrum and kanban
- Identify security vulnerabilities and make recommendations for remediation and make the necessary corrections
- Re-engineered company's systems setup by using scripting to automate server generation routines, optimizing system performance and establishing system monitoring, always maintaining security protocols
- Resolved system slow-down issues through network migrations, reconfiguration, integration, and troubleshooting

Universidad Nacional de Córdoba, Argentina Academic Researcher

January 2018 – January 2021

Responsible for planning, developing, and documenting "Natural Language Processing of the Latin American Spanish and Portuguese" scientific research. Key contributions include:

- Develop and perform Adapting Spanish Readability Metrics to Brazilian Portuguese
- Create libraries and scripts to detect languages
- Work closely with educational entities such as "Escuela para todos" and "Instituto Centroamericano de Extensión de la Cultura", ICECU
- Lecturer of scientific papers as research results, in events such as "International Conference on the Computational Processing of Portuguese", PROPOR 2018 (Brazil) and "II Coloquio Costarricense de Procesamiento del Lenguaje Natural" NLPCR18 (Costa Rica)

Instituto Tecnológico de Costa Rica Network Administrator

June 2014 - January 2018

Responsible for handling infrastructure provisioning, applications build-up, security patches, capacity management, incident, and problem management. Select responsibilities include:

- Maintain hardware and virtual infrastructure to safeguard data and maintain network stability
- Perform routine software and hardware maintenance
- Sustain network infrastructure by monitoring and maintaining uptime for access to District resources across all District work sites
- Coordinate and provide project management to deliver technology updates and implementations
- Provide quality assurance for system monitoring tools, including documentation monitoring processes and expanding automation
- Serve as subject matter expert on assigned network systems, and effectively communicate the development

Education

English course (TOEIC), Centro Cultural costarricense-norteamericano, CCCN 2022

Bachelor's degree in Computer Engineering, Instituto Tecnológico de Costa Rica, ITCR 2018

IT Essentials Cisco Networking Academy, Universidad Técnica Nacional, UTN 2016

Conare English Strengthening Program, Instituto Tecnológico de Costa Rica, ITCR 2018

Technical Skills

Operating Systems: Linux (Debian, Ubuntu, CentOS), Windows

Containers orchestration: Docker, Kubernetes, Rancher 1.x and Rancher 2.x

Databases: MySQL, MongoDB, SQLite, SQL

Virtual Infrastructure: AWS, Azure, Oracle VirtualBox, LXC, LXD, Proxmox

Cloud: OpenStack, Owncloud, AWS, VRA IBM Services: Apache2, Apache Tomcat, Nginx, IIS Scripting Languages: Bash, Perl, Python, bat

Languages Programming: C / C ++, C #, Java SE, Haskel, Groovy, Octave, Ruby

Version controller: Git

Languages

Spanish (Native) English (TOEIC)

Certification:

PCEP – Certified Entry-Level Python Programmer https://verify.openedg.org/?id=oocl.5DDY.1nTy DevOps Certification:

https://www.mundosecrm.com/certificado.php?i=bW9kZT1QREYmcmVjb3JkPTM5eDk5OTcyMg==

AWSPractitioner: 1M3H6W51PBB1Q9C7

Publications

- Analysis of images to identify specific user actions: https://ieeexplore.ieee.org/document/9105211
- Process-Based Assessment of Computer Science Students:
 https://ieeexplore.ieee.org/document/8783507
- Programming introduction course: https://gitlab.com/raraya23/curso-elementos-de-la-computacion